You may have heard
the expression
“knowledge is power.”
Well, today we’re going
to give you more power
to control your
diet and lifestyle
by giving you the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we learn about an herb
with impressive health benefits
that has long been used
in alternative medicine.
It’s called fenugreek and
its effects are remarkable.
"The effects of a commercially
available botanical supplement
on strength, body composition,
power output, and hormonal profiles
in resistance-trained males"
Something had a significant
impact on both upper and lower body
strength and body composition
in comparison to placebo
in a double-blind
controlled trial.
These changes were obtained
with no clinical side effects.
It allowed these men
to leg press an extra
hundred pounds compared
to placebo.
And the magical substance was...
Fenugreek.
A naturally occurring
edible spice
that appears to double
as an anti-cancer agent.
In summary, fenugreek
seeds may possess
potent anti-cancer
properties.
In our next story, we learn
that for all the benefits
of fenugreek seeds, they do
have an interesting side effect.
Cancer prevention is all well and good,
but there is a side effect of
fenugreek seed consumption—
it makes your armpits smell
like maple syrup.
“Analysis of human male armpit sweat
after fenugreek ingestion.”
And yes, it happens
to women, too.
“In this study, the strong
‘maple-syrup’ odour which appears
after fenugreek ingestion
was investigated.”
They had men plaster some
gauze pads undertheir armpits
before and after eating a tablespoon
of fenugreek seeds.
Sweat was collected
over a 24-hour period,
and given to a panel of eight
odor assessors to get their take.
They described what they smelled as
cocoa, roast beef,
carrots, spicy, gravy,
but then, honey,
rose and lilac,
peach-like, raspberry.
I guess it could be worse.
There was one assessor who described one of
the fenugreek odor compounds as
“[m]usty, sweet,
onion,socks.”
Another agreed, but thought it
more like “[f]ruity, floral, socks.”
Of course, there was the boring assessor who
was like, uh, smells like fenugreek.
This is a
harmless phenomenon;
the only reason I bring it up is that there
is actually a serious congenital disorder
called maple syrup urine disease:
branched-chain ketoaciduria.
It’s completely unrelated,
but breastfeeding infants,
with moms using fenugreek to boost their milk
production, may be misdiagnosed.
So, if you’re pregnant or breastfeeding,
and eating fenugreek,
make sure to tell your OB,
just so they don’t worry.
Finally today, we look at the
hormonal benefits of fenugreek.
In my video, the "Benefits of
Fenugreek Seeds," I profiled this study
in which young men were randomized
to a sugar pill or fenugreek capsules
for eight weeks and got a significant
improvement in upper body strength,
lower body strength,
and body composition,
a significant reduction
in body fat percentage.
And the only side effect?
It can make your sweat and
pee smell like maple syrup.
Seems like a bonus!
Studies on immature castrated rats
suggest the fenugreek muscle
bulking is a testosterone effect,
but we didn't know what
happens in humans...until now.
Four randomized controlled
trials put it to the test and
saw a significant boost
of total blood testosterone.
And indeed, fenugreek appears
to improve sexual function in men,
for example, doubling the
frequency of morning erections.
What about the sexual function
in women? While the estrogen
hormone, estradiol, stimulates
vaginal lubrication and blood flow,
facilitating a woman's capacity
for sexual arousal and orgasm,
it's the testosterone that's
linked with sexual desire
in both men and women.
Drug companies have tried
testosterone patches on women
to try to increase sexual desire,
but we're concerned
about blood clots
and long-term safety.
What about a little fenugreek?
A significant increase in
testosterone compared to placebo
and a boost in the estrogen estradiol,
which resulted in both an increase
in sexual desire and function,
translating into about a doubling
of sexual activity
compared to placebo.
If fenugreek causes an increase
in estrogen levels, what about
the efficacy of fenugreek for
reducing menopausal symptoms?
A significant reduction in menopausal
symptoms across every single domain,
for example, cutting the weekly
numbers of hot flashes and
night sweats in half over
a period of three months.
Other hormonal effects include
an improvement in painful periods.
What I like about this study is that
they didn't use some propriety extract,
but just straight, plain fenugreek
powder that you'd buy at the store.
Now, they packed it into capsules
just so they could pit it against
a sugar pill placebo,
but the dose they used
is just about a third of
a teaspoon three times a day,
taken the first three
days of their period.
A third of a teaspoon would
cost less than 5 cents.
And boom!
A significant decrease in pain,
and also appeared to improve
other symptoms as well.
While we're on a roll with hormonal
effects, what about the effectiveness
of fenugreek as a galactagogue?
No, not another sci-fi reboot.
A galactagogue is something that
increases breast milk production
in lactating mothers, and
fenugreek fits the bill.
And not just by a little.
In this randomized double-blind
placebo-controlled trial in which
breastfeeding women took less
than a quarter teaspoon of fenugreek,
less than a quarter teaspoon
of ground ginger,
and about a 16th of a teaspoon
of turmeric every day,
doubled their milk production
within a month,
about a 50% increase by week two
and a 100% increase by week four.
However, due to its potential
stimulation on the uterus,
fenugreek seeds should not
be used during pregnancy.
Though this is all based
on laboratory animal data,
better safe than sorry.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.